Finding Aid for the Hugh Davis Graham Collection
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
Hugh Davis Graham Collection
multiple
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
MSS.0543
.84 linear_feet
Biographical Note
Hugh Davis Graham was born September 2, 1936 and died on March 26, 2002 at his home in Santa Barbara, California at the age of 65. He was born in Little Rock, Arkansas, and spent his early years in Nashville, Tennessee.
He earned an undergraduate degree in history from Yale University in 1958, and then went on to complete his PhD in history from Stanford University in 1964. From 1967-1971, he worked as an associate professor and served as the director of the Institute of Southern History at Johns Hopkins University. Graham co-directed a task force for the National Commission on the Causes and Prevention of Violence in 1968-1969, as well as co-edited the commission’s report, Violence in America. He then went on to teach at the University of Maryland, Baltimore County until he was hired at Vanderbilt University in 1991.
At Vanderbilt he served as the Holland N. McTyeire Professor of History, Dean of Social Sciences, and Dean of Graduate Studies and Research. He won several major awards for his teaching and service, authored two books, and edited another two. During his time as Dean of Graduate Studies, he won several fellowships and grants, including a Guggenheim, the National Institute of Education, the American Enterprise Institute, and the Social Science Research Council. He was well known for his academic contributions to civil rights, southern politics, and policy history.
Professor Graham died just after the publication of his final book and just before a conference on the Reagan presidency that he had helped organize.
His publications include:
Violence in America: Historical and Comparative Perspectives. Ed. with Ted Robert Gurr. Washington: U.S. Government Printing Office. 1969.
Huey Long (Great Lives Observed). Prentice Hall. 1970.
Southern Politics and the Second Reconstruction. With Numan V. Bartley. Johns Hopkins University Press. 1976.
The Uncertain Triumph: Federal Education Policy in the Kennedy and Johnson Years. University of North Carolina Press. 1984.
The Civil Rights Era: Origins and Development of National Policy, 1960-1972. Oxford University Press. 1990.
Collision Course: The Strange Convergence of Affirmative Action and Immigration Policy in America. Oxford University Press. 2003.
The Rise of American Research Universities: Elites and Challengers in the Postwar Era. With Nancy Diamond. Johns Hopkins University Press. 2004.
Scope and Content Note
The Hugh Davis Graham is a small collection of two Hollinger boxes (.83 linear feet) the biggest part of which are his published articles. Also in the collection are notes, programs from conferences, newspaper clippings, research, and emails. Most of the content in the Hugh Davis Graham Collection relates to his interests in Civil Rights and Policy History, more specifically the Civil Rights Act and Affirmative Action.
- Writings
  - Articles, (Spring 1987 – September 1992) (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - “The Paradox of Eleanor Roosevelt: Alcoholism’s Child”, Virginia Quarterly Review Vol. 63, Spring 1987 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - “Race, Language, and Social Policy: Comparing the Black and Hispanic Experience in the U.S .”, Population and Environment Vol. 12, Fall 1990 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - “Voting Rights and the American Regulatory State, Controversies in Minority Voting”, Controversies in Minority Voting, May 1992 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - “The Origins of Affirmative Action: Civil Rights and the Regulatory State”, The Annals Vol. 523 (2 copies), September 1992 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Spring 1993 – “The Stunted Career of Policy History: A Critique and an Agenda”, The Public Historian Vol. 15 (x2), Articles (Spring 1993 – 1995) (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - “ Race, History, and Policy: African Americans and Civil Rights since 1964”, Civil Rights in the United States 1994 – “Legislatures and Civil Rights”, Encyclopedia of the American Legislative System Vol. 3, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - “The Limits of Public Law Litigation”, Legal Studies Forum Vol. 19, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Articles, (Winter 1996 – 1998) (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - “Richard Nixon and Civil Rights: Explaining an Enigma”, Presidential Studies Quarterly Vol. 26 (x3), Winter 1996 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - “An Issue Transformed: How Immigration Is Changing the Debate Over Affirmative Action, and Vice Versa”, The Social Contract Vol. 6, Summer 1996 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - “The Storm Over Grove City College: Civil Rights Regulation, Higher Education, and the Reagan Administration”, History of Education Quarterly Vol. 38 (x2), Winter 1998 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - “The Politics of Clientele Capture: Civil Rights Policy and the Reagan Administration”, Redefining Equality, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - “Legacies of the 1960’s: The American “Rights Revolution” in an Era of Divided Governance”, Journal of Policy History Vol. 10, Articles (1998-2000) 1998 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - “The Surprising Career of Federal Fair Housing Law”, Journal of Policy History Vol. 12, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Book chapters written by HDG (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - July 1996, The South as an American Problem, Since 1965: The South and Civil Rights January 1998 – Redefining Equality, Ch. 7: The Politics of Clientele Capture (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Book chapters written by others (1 of 3) (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Strangers to the Constitution by Gerald L. Newman, Ch. 7 Crossing the Border, July 1996 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Ch. 8 Limits of the Polity (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Books chapters by others (2 of 3) (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Chapter 7: Bilingual Education and Language Rights in the Schools, book unknown (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Book chapters by others (3 of 3) (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Chapter 8: Women’s Rights and the Origins of Title IX: Separate but Equal in College Sports (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - “Presumptions for Preferences: The Small Business Administration’s Decisions on Groups Entitled to Affirmative Action” by George R. LaNoue and John C. Sullivan, Journal of Policy History Vol. 4, Articles by others 1994 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - “Who Should Get In?” by Christopher Jenks, November 2001 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Book reviews by HDG (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence about book reviews (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Writings that Cite HDG (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - “The Great Society after Johnson: The Case of Bilingual Education” by Gareth Davies, The Journal of American History, March 2002 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - “The Small Business Administration and the Origins of Black Capitalism”, unknown date and author (Box 2, Folder 1)
- --Academic Career
  - Levy Institute Conference, September 2000 – “The Origin of Official Minority Designation” (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Levy Institute Conference, September 2000 (1 of 3) (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Levy Institute Conference, September 2000 (2 of 3) (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Levy Institute Conference, September 2000 (3 of 3) (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Living Wage Ordinance – Research Materials (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - African American Encyclopedia (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Great Society UVA – “The Great Society’s Civil Rights Legacy” (Box 2, Folder 7)